Guide to the Judson Crews Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Judson Crews papers
1930-1991
YCAL MSS 536
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.44
(41 boxes)
The Judson Crews Papers provide evidence of the personal and professional life of American poet Judson Crews between 1930 and 1991. The papers document Crews' career as a poet, printer, and small-press publisher, and consist of correspondence, writings, and personal papers. Crews and his wife Mildred Tolbert, a photographer and writer, were members of the artistic community in Taos, New Mexico in the mid twentieth-century. There is also some material relating to Crews' friendship with Henry Miller. Correspondents include Crews' daughters Anna Bush Crews and Carole Judith Crews as well as Wendell B. Anderson, Carol Bergé, and J. Whitebird.
Crews, Judson, 1917-2010
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Judson Crews, 1972-1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Judson Crews (1917-2010)
Judson Campbell Crews, American author and small-press publisher, was born on June 30, 1917, in Waco, Texas, the youngest of seven children born to Noah George and Tommie Farmer Crews. Following his father's suicide in 1936, Crews worked as a landscape architect in Waco. He then attended Baylor University (A.B., 1941). Crews also started publishing a number of literary magazines, including Vers Libre (1937) and Motive (1940), the latter established along with Crew's bookstore of the same name.
Following graduation Crews published his first book of poetry, Psalms for a Late Season, which was printed by Iconograph Press (1942). Crews served with the U.S. Army Medical Corps during World War II (1942-1944). After which Crews completed a Master of Arts in sociology and psychology (1944) from Baylor University and studied fine arts (1946-1947). Following graduation Crews moved out West, spending time in Washington, Oregon, and California, where he befriended Henry Miller, a relationship he later reflected on in his books Henry Miller and My Big Sur Days: Vignettes From Memory (1992) and The Brave Wild Coast: A Year with Henry Miller (1997).
After living in California Crews moved to Taos, New Mexico, where he established Este Es Press (1946-1966) and worked as a printer for Taos Star, El Crepusculo, and Taos News Publishing Co (1948-1966).
Crews and Mildred Tolbert (1919-2008), a photographer and writer, were married on October 19, 1947. Crews and Tolbert had two daughters: Anna Bush Crews (1948-) and Carole Judith Crews (1950-).
While in Taos, Crews continued to publish literary magazines such as The Flying Fish (1948), The Deer and Dachshund, in collaboration with Tolbert and Wendell Anderson, which continued on as Suck-Egg Mule (1951), Taos (1951), Poetry Taos (1957), and The Naked Ear. In addition to publishing authors such as Robert Creeley, Charles Bukowski, and Carol Bergé, Crews also published his own writings including The Heart in Naked Hunger (1958), Inwade to Briney Garth (1960), A Unicorn When Needs Be (1963), Hermes Past the Hour (1963), and Angels Fall, They Are Towers (1965). Throughout his career Crews wrote under several pseudonyms, including Willard Emory Betis, Trumbull Drachler, Charley John Greasybear, Cerise Farallon, and Toby Macadams.
Crews returned to graduate school at the University of Texas at El Paso in 1967. At various points in his career Crews balanced his artistic life with careers in social work and as an educator in sociology and psychology. Crews was employed as a caseworker for the El Paso Country Child Welfare Unit (1966-1967), instructor for Wharton Junior College, Wharton, Texas (1967-1970), psychological counselor and community services coordinator for Community Mental Health Service, Gallup, New Mexico ( 1970-1971), lecturer at the University of New Mexico Branch College, Gallup, New Mexico (1971-1972), and director of the intensive care unit at the State School for Girls, Chillicothe, Missouri (1973).
Following a separation from Mildred Tolbert in 1972, Crews moved to Africa where he was a lecturer in social development studies at the University of Zambia, Lusaka (1974-1978). While in Africa Crews began writing an autobiography, which remains unpublished. Following his return to the United States, Crews and Tolbert finalized their divorced (1979). Crews returned to Taos where he published more books, including a collection of poems The Clock of Moss (1983) edited by Carol Bergé.
Crews died in Taos, New Mexico, on May 17th 2010.
Mildred Tolbert was born in Amarillo, Texas on January 8, 1919. After two years of college Tolbert moved to Taos where she practiced photography, a skill she later taught as a civilian photography instructor at Lowry Field in Denver, Colorado (1943). Tolbert worked in photography laboratories (including Leco Photo Service) in New York for two years before returning to Taos. Tolbert studied literature at the University of Texas at El Paso (1966) and the University of Houston (where she graduated with a bachelor of arts in 1970). In 1973 Tolbert received a fellowship from the Helene Wurlitzer Foundation of New Mexico, an artist residence program based in Taos. Tolbert's works were included in exhibitions at the Shipley Gallery (2005) and the Harwood Museum (2006). Crews died in Ranchos de Taos, New Mexico, on January 22, 2008.
Scope and Contents
The Judson Crews Papers provide evidence of the personal and professional life of American poet Judson Crews between 1930 and 1991. The papers document Crews' career as a poet, printer, and small-press publisher, and consist of correspondence, writings, and personal papers. As the Papers illustrate, Crews and his wife Mildred Tolbert, a photographer and writer, were members of the artistic community in Taos, New Mexico in the mid-twentieth-century. There is also some material relating to Crews' friendship with Henry Miller.
Crews' creative life is reflected in his writings and correspondence. The papers include various drafts of his poetry and other writing projects, such as "Henry Miller and the Millennial Oranges of Big Sur," and an unpublished memoir. Some manuscripts are listed under Crews' pen names, such as Charley John Greasybear, Cerise Farallon, and Toby Macadams. Crews' correspondence similarly reflects his literary circle, with correspondents including Joanie Whitebird, who was a writer, editor, publisher, and founder of Wings Press, Phil Nurenberg of Happy Rock Press, and poet Carol Bergé. There are also letters between Crews and Wendell Anderson, a friend and collaborator who also wrote a thesis on Crews titled A Critical Analysis of Poems by a Contemporary Poet of the Avant-Garde: Judson Crews (a copy of which is in the papers). The Papers also include the work of other artists, such as photographs by Mildred Tolbert and writings by Carol Bergé, Wendell Anderson, and others.
Crews' personal life is recorded in his correspondence with his wife Mildred Tolbert, daughters Anna Bush Crews and Carole Judith Crews, as well as Carol Bergé, with whom he was involved romantically.
To a lesser degree the papers relate to Crews' career as a social worker and instructor, with correspondence regarding the New Mexico Department of Hospitals and Institutions, Crews' Master's Thesis on The Treatment of Social Problems in Recent Southern Literature, and teaching materials.
Arrangement
Organized into eleven groupings: I. 1972-1980 Acquisitions, 1930-1983. II. August 1986 Acquisition, 1984-1985. III. July 1987 Acquisition, 1982-1987. IV. August 1987 Acquisition, 1982-1987. V. May 1989 Acquisition, 1987-1988. VI. January 1990 Acquisition, 1981-1989. VII. April 1990 Acquisition, undated. VIII. November 1990 Acquisition, 1978-1981. IX. February 1991 Acquisition, undated. X. August 1991 Acquisition, 1984-1991. XI. Undated Acquisition, 1980-1984.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with or relates to material found in other acquisitions (e.g., correspondence, writings, and personal papers can be found in all groupings). In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers should consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors and publishers -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Small presses -- United States; Authors -- Taos (N.M.) -- 20th Century; Poets -- Taos (N.M.) -- 20th Century; Anderson, Wendell B.; Bergé, Carol, 1928-2006; Crews, Anna Bush; Crews, Carole Judith; Crews, Judson, 1917-2010; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Tolbert, Mildred; Whitebird, J.
- I. 1972-1980 Acquisitions, 1930-1983; 11.68; (28 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence and drafts of writings.
  Former call number: Za Crews
  - Collection list and notes, circa 1970 (Box 1)
  - Prose writings, typescript, corrected, 1930s-1940s; 5 (Box 1)
  - Rape of the Innocent... Rape of the Damned, typescript carbon, 1946; 2 (Box 1)
  - I Have No Pleasure in Them, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings and notes, 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
  - Poetry typescripts and manuscripts, 1963-1969; 5 (Box 2)
  - Poetry typescripts and manuscripts, 1947-1970; 5 (Box 3)
  - Photographs by Mildred Tolbert, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Pat Barela sculptures, undated (Box 3)
  - The Treatment of Social Problems in Recent Southern Literature, Masters Thesis, typescript, 1944; 4 (Box 4)
  - A Tyranny of Tears, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - The Unnecessary Serpent, typescript, undated (Box 4)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1973; 3 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973; 3 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1973; 2 (Box 6)
  - Poetry typescripts and manuscripts, 1969-1973, undated; 3 (Box 6)
  - List of June 1980 acquisition (Box 7)
  - Poetry typescripts and manuscripts, 1933-1948; 7 (Box 7)
  - Poetry typescripts, 1950-1968; 7 (Box 8)
  - Poetry typescripts, 1968-1972, 1978-1979, undated; 5 (Box 9)
  - "Willard Emory Batis," typescript poems, 1953 (Box 9)
  - "Trumbull Drachler," typescript poems, 1953 (Box 9)
  - Poetry typescripts, undated (Box 10)
  - Anderson, Wendell, correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Anderson, Wendell. A Critical Analysis of a Group of Poems by a Contemporary Poet of the Avant-Garde, Judson Crews, typescript, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1975-1980; 2 (Box 10)
    Also includes letters from Anna Bush Crews and Carole Crews.
  - "Cerise Farallon," typescript poems, undated (Box 11)
  - "Toby Macadams," typescript poems, undated (Box 11)
  - Rape of the Innocent... Rape of the Damned, typescript, corrected, 1978 July 26; 2 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, rejection letters, and typescripts, 1975-1980; 3 (Box 11)
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, letters to Mildred Tolbert, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Poetry related mailings and printed material, undated (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, typescript poems, and printed material, 1959-1970; 6 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1967-1971; 5 (Box 13)
  - Newspapers, 1959-1960 (Box 13)
  - Teaching materials and correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1972; 8 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1972; 5 (Box 15)
  - Crews, Carole and Anna Bush Crews, correspondence, circa 1970 (Box 15)
  - Poems, typescript, undated (Box 15)
  - Anderson, Wendell B., correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Crews, Carole and Anna Bush Crews, correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1981 (Box 16)
  - Whitebird, Joanie, correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 16)
  - "Henry Miller and the Millennial Oranges of Big Sur," manuscript and typescript draft, undated (Box 16)
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, correspondence, 1983, undated; 6 (Box 17)
  - Benedetti, David. "Beautiful Vulva," typescript, 1952 (Box 17)
  - Benedetti, David. Mounting Information Text: A Computer-Written Novel Programmed by David Benedetti, typescript, 1981 March 29 (Box 17)
  - Bergé, Carol. Secrets, Gossip and Slander: A Novel, typescript (photocopy), 1981 August (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, periodicals, etc., 1982-1983; 6 (Box 17)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, circa 1983; 8 (Box 17)
  - "Fuck Nukes," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 18)
  - The Noose, manuscript notes and correspondence, 1978 (Box 18)
  - Poems, typescript and manuscript, 1975-1979 (Box 18)
  - Personal papers, with letters by him and notes for his works, undated (Box 18)
  - Macnab, Alexander. Poems, typescript, undated (Box 18)
  - Macnab, Maggie. "Symmetrical Dualisms," typescript, undated (Box 18)
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, correspondence, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Byrd, Bobby, correspondence and typescripts, undated (Box 18)
  - Crews, Carole and Anna Bush Crews, correspondence, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Gonzales, Arden, correspondence and typescripts, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Whitebird, Joanie, correspondence and typescripts, 1979-1980 (Box 18)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 18)
  - Broadsides, clippings, pamphlets, etc., undated (Box 18)
  - Anderson, Wendell, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 19)
  - Unsorted correspondence, typescripts, and printed material, 1970-1979; 4 (Box 19)
  - Crews, Carole, correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 19)
  - Crews, Anna Bush, correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 19)
  - Unsorted correspondence, mainly with editors of poetry publications, circa 1970-1977; 7 (Box 20)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, letters to Judson Crews and Anna Bush Crews, 1974-1979; 7 (Box 21)
  - UNZA papers and correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 22)
  - The Apprentice, Literary Quarterly, 1934 (Box 22)
  - Guggenheim application writing samples, typescript, undated (Box 22)
  - Personal papers, correspondence, and typescripts, undated (Box 22)
  - Whitebird, Joanie, correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence about New Mexico Department of Hospitals and Institutions, 1971 (Box 22)
  - Unsorted correspondence, mostly with Mildred Tolbert and Carol Bergé, undated (Box 22)
  - Wengler, Joan, correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 22)
  - Anderson, Wendell, correspondence, 1973-1978; 2 (Box 22)
  - Poems, typescript, manuscript, and typescript (photocopy), 1939-1979, undated; 7 (Box 23)
  - Poems, typescript and typescript (photocopy), 1947-1976, undated; 8 (Box 24)
  - "Lusaka," poems, manuscript, 1974-1975; 3 (Box 24)
  - Anderson, Wendell B. Poems, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 8 (Box 25)
  - Anderson, Wendell B. Poems, typescript and typescript carbon, 1960, undated; 8 (Box 26)
  - Bergé, Carol. Correspondence and typescripts, undated (Box 26)
  - "Charley John Greasybear," correspondence and typescripts, 1978 (Box 26)
  - Unsorted correspondence, typescripts and manuscripts, and printed material, 1974-1979; 3 (Box 26)
  - Poems, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 26)
  - Anderson, Wendell B., correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box 27)
  - Anderson, Wendell B. A Blossom Burning Against Time, typescript, undated (Box 27)
  - Anderson, Wendell B. A Critical Analysis of a Group of Poems by a Contemporary Poet of the Avant-Garde, Judson Crews, typescript (photocopy), 1969 (Box 28)
- II. August 1986 Acquisition, 1984-1985; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, and a manuscript draft memoir by Crews.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 13.
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, 1984-1985 (Box 29)
  - Bergé, Carol, 1984 (Box 29)
    Also contains photographs.
  - Nurenburg, Phil, 1984 (Box 29)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, 1984-1985; 2 (Box 29)
  - Memoir, 1917-1927, manuscript draft, undated; 5 (Box 30)
    Pages 1-833
- III. July 1987 Acquisition, 1982-1987; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains incoming correspondence.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 39.
  - Tolbert, Mildred, circa 1986 (Box 31)
  - Nurenburg, Phil, 1984-1985 (Box 31)
  - McLaughlin, John, 1983-1986 (Box 31)
  - Crews, Anna Bush, 1982-1986 (Box 31)
  - Crews, Carole, 1982-1987 (Box 31)
- IV. August 1987 Acquisition, 1982-1987; 1.25; (1 box)
  Contains a draft of Crews's autobiography, manuscript draft poems, and correspondence.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 46.
  - [Autobiography], typescript, corrected, undated; 10 (Box 32)
    Pages numbered 8201-9631.
  - Poetry manuscripts, 1982-1984; 2 (Box 32)
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 32)
  - Nurenburg, Phil, correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 32)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1987 (Box 32)
  - Photograph of Crews by Mildred Tolbert and finding aid for Arden Tice Papers at University of New Mexico, undated (Box 32)
  - Bergé, Carol, correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 32)
- V. May 1989 Acquisition, 1987-1988; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains correspondence, a draft of Wendell Anderson's "Taos and This Far South," and assorted short writings.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 95.
  - Anderson, Wendell and Emily, correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 33)
  - Anderson, Wendell. "Taos and This Far South," typescript draft (photocopy), undated (Box 33)
  - Essays and autobiographical writings, typescript and manuscript, undated (Box 33)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1988 (Box 33)
- VI. January 1990 Acquisition, 1981-1989; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains correspondence, primarily incoming; as well as photocopies of typescripts of The Ultimate Minotaur and The Anatomy of a Centaur; manuscript draft poems; and a typescript photocopy of Wendell Anderson's "Taos and This Far South."
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 122.
  - Whitebird, Joanie, correspondence, circa 1981-1987 (Box 34)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1989 (Box 34)
  - Editors, etc., 1982-1987 (Box 34)
    Contains correspondence to Crews from the editors of a variety of magazines and other publications.
  - The Ultimate Minotaur, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 34)
  - The Anatomy of a Centaur, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 34)
  - "Poetry Manuscripts," manuscript drafts, 1984-1988; 2 (Box 34)
    Pages numbered 2701-3146.
  - Anderson, Wendell. "Taos and This Far South," typescript (photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 34)
- VII. April 1990 Acquisition, undated; 1; (1 box)
  Contains an undated draft of Crews's autobiography.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 132.
  - [Autobiography] "Copy #1," manuscript and typescript draft, undated; 15 (Box 35)
    Pages numbered 4951-6400.
- VIII. November 1990 Acquisition, 1978-1981; 0.21; (1 box)
  Contains primarily incoming correspondence, with enclosures of poems, photographs, and printed material.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 168.
  - Bergé, Carol, circa 1978-1981; 3 (Box 36)
- IX. February 1991 Acquisition, undated; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Contains photocopied drafts of unidentified writings.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 171.
  - Unidentified writing [Autobiography], typescript (photocopy), undated; 5 (Box 37)
    Pages numbered 6551-7300.
  - Unidentified writing [Autobiography], "Copy #2," manuscript (photocopy), undated; 3 (Box 37)
    Pages numbered 4201-4650.
  - Unidentified writing [Autobiography], "Copy #2," manuscript (photocopy), undated; 2 (Box 38)
    Pages numbered 4651-4950.
- X. August 1991 Acquisition, 1984-1991; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains incoming correspondence and manuscript poems.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 188.
  - Anderson, Wendell, correspondence, 1988-1991; 3 (Box 39)
  - Tolbert, Mildred, correspondence, 1989-1990; 2 (Box 39)
  - "Poetry manuscripts," holograph drafts, 1984-1989; 2 (Box 39)
    Pages numbered 2966-3100, 3147-3300.
- XI. Undated Acquisition, 1980-1984; 0.42; (1 box)
  Contains primarily correspondence between Carol Bergé and Crews, with a small amount of correspondence from Bergé to third parties.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 379 and Zab C867 +1.
  - Bergé, Carol, 1980-1984; 7 (Box 40)
  - "Judson Crews," Poetry Now, Volume 6, Number 6, 1982 (Box 41)